"Is Soy Milk the Most Nutritious
Non-Dairy Milk?"
There is a constellation
of new choices
in the dairy case these days,
from almonds to oats,
such that major dairy corporations
are going out of business.
But a set of recommendations
on healthy beverage choice
from like 12 to 24 months
of age cautioned
that these plant-based milks are not
adequate nutritional substitutes
for dairy milk, with the exception
of fortified soy milk.
The report and the press coverage
immediately triggered an outcry
from the medical community
for many reasons
including the concern around
conflicts of interests,
as several of these endorsing
organizations received funds
from the dairy industry, though
one such organization is accused
of trying to cover that fact up
by removing the National Dairy
Council from their list of sponsors
immediately after
the report was released.
But what about
the merits of the report?
Well, after weaning, milk
of any kind is not required
and really shouldn't be relied upon
as a main source of calories.
Children will be fine with
water and healthy food.
If you are going
to give kids milk,
there would seem
to be a better choice.
Although cow's milk
is rich in calcium,
it does not appear
to clearly reduce fractures
and most plant-based milks on
the market have the same amount.
More importantly, the consumption
of cow's milk carries risks
including a potential association
with type 1 diabetes onset,
anemia in toddlers,
lactose intolerance,
cow's milk protein allergy,
and infantile colic.
I've got a bunch of videos
on those topics.
So the adverse effects from
just normal consumption
of cow's milk must be
compared against the risks
from plant-based milks,
which are problematic
mainly when used inappropriately,
meaning like to the exclusion
of most other foods: diets that
are clearly inappropriate,
like the case of kwashiorkor
in Atlanta,
because his diet was
basically 99% rice milk.
Plant-based milks
have the benefit
of being low in saturated fat,
free of cholesterol,
and though the protein content is
generally lower than in cow's milk,
plant-based milks are said
to be richer in terms of fiber.
That's technically true, since
cow's milk has zero fiber,
but the fiber contents of plant-
based milks are pretty pitiful,
certainly compared to the whole
foods from which they were derived.
I mean, a cup of soybeans themselves
would have more than 10 grams,
but still soy milk is likely
the least processed
out of all plant-based milks.
It's basically just soak,
crush, cook, and strain,
and is said to be the only
non-dairy milk that contains
the same amount
of protein as cow's milk.
That may have once been true,
but now there's pea milk, which
is also comparable protein-wise.
They all tend to have the same
calcium and vitamin D levels
and fewer calories,
as many as five times fewer
calories than cow's milk, in fact.
Soy milk has the additional
benefit of reducing
breast cancer risk in girls and
normalizing development.
Soy milk consumption
is also associated
with lower prostate
cancer risk in men.
And interventional studies
suggest improved gut health
by boosting the growth
of good bacteria.
Soy milk has
anti-inflammatory effects,
lowering c-reactive protein levels,
has desirable effects on phosphorus
metabolism compared to cow's milk,
significantly reduces free radical
DNA damage compared
to rice milk or cow's milk,
prevents bone loss in
postmenopausal women
when put to the test,
and can improve
insulin resistance.
Soy milk can help
with stroke rehab,
improving walking speed,
exercise endurance,
grip strength, and
muscle functionality,
as well as lower blood pressure
in men and women better
than cow's milk, not to mention
lowering your LDL cholesterol
as much as 25%
after just 21 days.
It is quite clear that nutritionally
soy milk is the best alternative
for replacing cow's milk
in the human diet.
Yes, there are all
sorts of benefits
of plant-based versus
udder-based milks.
No casein, cholesterol,
lactose, less saturated fat,
actually has a bit of fiber,
but what about the specter
of anti-nutrients?
Is there even such
a thing as anti-nutrients?
Longstanding evidence suggests
that consuming a diet
rich in plant-based foods plays
a significant role in prevention
and reduction of chronic diseases,
such as cardiovascular disease,
cancer, stroke, dementia,
diabetes, cataracts, and others.
Despite the need to increase
plant-food consumption,
there have been some
concerns raised about
whether they are beneficial
because of the various
so-called anti-nutrient
compounds they contain.
It's true there are some
compounds when eaten
in high enough quantities --
especially when taken
in isolation -- that can
have adverse effects.
Whole plant foods also contain
thousands of other compounds
in the food matrix,
though, many of which
counteract the potential
effects of the anti-nutrients.
Plant-based diets are associated
with a reduced risk of lifestyle-
induced chronic diseases.
The thousands of phytonutrients
they contain
promote antioxidant defense,
for example, reduce inflammation.
In some cases, what has been
referred to as anti-nutrients
may, in fact, be therapeutic
agents for various conditions.
See, for example, my video
series on the role of phytates
in the prevention and
treatment of cancer.
I don't want to end
without emphasizing
one of the plant-based pros:
no lactose.
People don't understand that
the majority of adult humans
on Planet Earth are unable
to digest cow's milk.
Throughout childhood, the enzyme
you have that breaks down
the milk sugar lactose begins
to decline in most individuals
throughout the world, which makes
sense since milk is for babies.
Why would we need to digest it
after weaning from the breast?
And so most people experience
symptoms like bloating,
abdominal pain, intestinal gas,
and watery stool, or even
nausea and vomiting.
The global prevalence estimate
of lactose malabsorption
is more than 2 out of 3 people;
in the United States,
it's more like 1 out of 3.
But 95% of Asians,
60% to 80% of African Americans
and Ashkenazi Jews,
80% to 100 % of American Indians,
and 50 to 80 % of Hispanics
have trouble digesting milk.
It's really mostly those
of northern European origin
who can handle it
throughout adulthood.
So to say everyone should drink
milk seems like an example
of racial bias in
federal nutrition policy.
It's like they're assuming everyone
is of Northern European descent.
Overall, about 75%
of the world's population,
including 25% of those
in the United States,
lose their lactase enzymes
after weaning.
To fight
the vitamin D disease rickets,
they had to choose something in the
food supply to fortify with vitamin D.
Choosing dairy is ironic,
since individuals of African ancestry,
because of their darker skin,
are at particularly high risk
for vitamin D deficiency,
yet most can't properly digest it.
But there is some good news.
For reasons like these,
Canada has recently removed
dairy as a separate food group
in their national dietary guidance.
In 2019, the new Canada's
Dietary Guidelines and food guide
were released, having undergone
a thorough review and update
to emphasize the
importance of consuming
more plant-based products.
Another major change was
the removal of dairy
as a separate food group
with --- wait for it ---
water included
as the beverage of choice.
What a concept.
The attenuated emphasis
on dairy products
and the increased focus on
plant-based foods in Canada
were based on several parameters,
including the removal
of industry-funded studies
from consideration
as part of the evidence base.